Good morning, everyone.
大家好 各位
Glad you are all here bright and early.
很高兴你们都早早来了  看起来不错嘛
I'm counting the days till the TA's outnumber the students.
我在数什么时候这个课上助教的人数会比学生多
They'll show up. We return to a familiar story.
好吧他们会来的 来来来 开始上课
This is part two, the Empire Strikes Back.
今天讲的是星战第二部分  帝国反击战
So last time, our adversary,
所以 在上一次 我们的对手
the graph, came to us with a problem.
图先生  带着问题找到了我们
We have a source, and we had a directed graph,
我们有一个源 我们有一个有向图
and we had weights on the edges,
我们有每条边的权重
and they were all nonnegative.
而且它们都是非负数
And there was happiness.
这就是我们喜闻乐见的
And we triumphed over the
我们通过构建一个Dijkstra算法
Empire by designing Dijkstra's algorithm,
从而击败了这个帝国
and very efficiently finding single source shortest paths,
然后非常效率地找到了单源最短路径
shortest path weight from s to every other vertex.
从s到每个其余顶点地最短路径
Today, however, the Death Star has a new trick up its sleeve,
但是今天  死星有了一个新的把戏
and we have negative weights, potentially.
我们有潜在的负权值
And we're going to have to somehow deal with,
不管怎样我们还是要解决
in particular, negative weight cycles.
具体来说就是负权环的问题
And we saw that when we have a negative weight cycle,
当我们发现出现了一个负权环
we can just keep going around, and around, and around,
我们只能让它一圈一圈一圈地运行
and go back in time farther, and farther, and farther.
然后时间就这么走啊走啊走啊
And we can get to be arbitrarily far back in the past.
这种循环可以无穷无尽地进行下去
And so there's no shortest path,
所以这里并不存在最短路径
because whatever path you take you can get a shorter one.
因为无论你选择那条路径  你都能得到一条更短的
So we want to address that issue today,
所以今天我们来讨论一下这个问题
and we're going to come up with
我们将要说到
a new algorithm actually simpler than Dijkstra,
一个实际上比Dijkstra的还简单的新算法
but not as fast, called the Bellman-Ford algorithm.
虽然没有它快 我们把它叫做Bellman－Ford算法
And, it's going to allow negative weights,
这个算法将允许负权数存在
and in some sense allow negative weight cycles,
并且在某种程度上接受负权环
although maybe not as much as you might hope.
虽然接受程度可能没有你们想象地那么高
We have to leave room for a sequel, of course.
当然 我们得给结论留些空间
OK, so the Bellman-Ford algorithm,
好了 所以 Bellman-Ford算法——
invented by two guys, as you might expect,
是由两个人发明的——估计你们也猜到了
it computes the shortest path weights.
它可以计算出最短路径权重
So, it makes no assumption about the weights.
因此 它对权值没有限制
Weights are arbitrary, and
权值是任意的  并且
it's going to compute the shortest path weights.
它计算的是最短途径权重
So, remember this notation: delta , s,v
所以 请记得这个记号  δ(s,v)
is the weight of the shortest path from s to v.
表示从s到v的最短途径权值
s was called a source vertex.
s被称作源顶点
And, we want to compute
然后我们要计算出
these weights for all vertices, little v.
所有这些顶点的权数  用小写v
The claim is that computing from s to everywhere
结论是 计算从s到任意一点的路径
is no harder than computing s to a particular location.
并不比计算s到某个顶点难
So, we're going to do for all them.
所以 我们把到所有点的路径全都算一遍
It's still going to be the case here.
不过在这里还是有个问题
And, it allows negative weights.
它允许负权数
And this is the good case, but there's an alternative,
这有利有弊
which is that Bellman-Ford may just say, oops,
Bellman－ford可能会说   矮油
there's a negative weight cycle.
负权环出现了
And in that case it will just say so.
它会告诉我们负权环在刷存在感
So, they say a negative weight cycle exists.
那么  负权环是存在的
Therefore, some of these deltas are minus infinity.
因此这里有些δ是负无穷的
And that seems weird.
这就很诡异了
So, Bellman-Ford as we'll
所以 Bellman-Ford算法——
present it today is intended for the case,
就是我们一会儿要说的 它其实是给
where there are no negative weights cycles,
没有负权环的问题而构造的
which is more intuitive.
因为这样更直观一点
It sort of allows them, but it will just report them.
其实可以说它是允许负权环存在的  但它只是会检测出来
In that case, it will not give you delta values.
在这种情况下它不会给你δ的值
You can change the algorithm
当然你可以修改算法
to give you delta values in that case,
来帮你算出δ值
but we are not going to see it here.
我们这里先不讲
So, in exercise, after you see the algorithm, exercise is:
不过嘛 学完这个算法 留给你们的作业就是
compute these deltas in all cases.
计算出所有的δ
So, it's not hard to do.
这做起来并不困难
But we don't have time for it here.
但我们在这里没有时间做了
So, here's the algorithm. It's pretty straightforward.
那么  现在我们来讲这个算法   它很直观
As I said, it's easier than Dijkstra.
正如我所说的  它比Dijkstra的算法还要简单
It's a relaxation algorithm.
它是一个松弛算法
So the main thing that it does
它的主体思想就是
is relax edges just like Dijkstra.
像Dijkstra所做的那样对边进行松弛
So, we'll be able to use a lot of dilemmas from Dijkstra.
我们能够用到许多的来自Dijkstra的推论
And proof of correctness will be three times shorter
与此同时  证明所用的时间将会缩短3倍
because of the first two thirds we already have from Dijkstra.
因为起初的2/3部分我们已经从Dijkstra得到了
But I'm jumping ahead a bit.
一不小心多讲了一点
So, the first part is initialization.
那么  这第一个部分是初始化
Again, d of v will represent
然后 d[v]代表了
the estimated distance from s to v.
从s到v的估计距离
And we're going to be updating those estimates
然后 在算法的运行过程中
as the algorithm goes along.
我们不断更新这些估值
And initially, d of s is zero,
初始化的时候  d(s)=0
which now may not be the right answer conceivably.
不过现在这可不一定是正确答案
Everyone else is infinity,
剩下的都是无穷大
which is certainly an upper bound.
当然无穷大也是一个实际的值
OK, these are both upper bounds on the true distance.
这些最大值都有一个具体的值
So that's fine.
这就相当给力了
That's initialization just like before.
这是和前面一样的初始化
And now we have a main loop
现在我们有一个主循环
which happens v minus one times.
循环了v-1次
We're not actually going to use the index i.
我们实际上不会用到变量i
It's just a counter.
它只是一个计数器
And we're just going to look at every edge and relax it.
然后我们考察每一条边  并对它进行松弛操作
It's a very simple idea. If you learn about relaxation,
这是一个很简单的想法  如果你刚开始学松弛操作的话
this is the first thing you might try.
你应该先试试这么做
The question is when do you stop.
问题在于你何时停止
It's sort of like I have this friend who when he was
这有点类似于  我有一个朋友
six years old he would claim,
在他6岁的时候他会说
oh, I know how to spell banana.
矮油  我知道香蕉这个单词怎么拼了
I just don't know when to stop.
我只是不知道什么时候结束
OK, same thing with relaxation.
好吧  这和松弛操作是一样的
This is our relaxation step just as before.
这是我们的松弛操作  就像之前一样
We look at the edge;
我们看着这个边
we see whether it violates the triangle inequality
观察它是否违反了三角不等式
according to our current estimates we know the distance
根据我们现在的测算  我们知道
from s to v should be at most distance
s到v的距离至多是
from s to u plus the weight of that edge from u to v.
s到u的距离再加上从u到v的那条边的权重
If it isn't, we set it equal.
如果不是  我们将它们设为相等
We've proved that this is always an OK thing to do.
我们已经证明了这一直是一个正确的操作
We never violate, I mean,
我的意思是  它不会违背——
these d of v's never get too small
这些d[v]的距离绝对不会变的太小
if we do a bunch of relaxations.
如果我们做了一连串的松弛操作
So, the idea is you take every edge.
所以 基本思路是你算每一条边
You relax it. I don't care which order.
都去松弛它  顺序什么的无所谓
Just relax every edge, one each.
只是松弛每一条边就行了  每次一条
And that do that V minus one times.
然后松弛v-1次
The claim is that that should be enough
这应该是足够的
if you have no negative weights cycles.
不过仅限于没有负权环的时候
So, if there's a negative weight cycle,
那么  如果这里出现了负权环
we need to figure it out.
我们需要把它检测出来
And, we'll do that in a fairly straightforward way,
我们将用一个相当直接的方法来做
which is we're going to do exactly the same thing.
我们做的是完全一样的事
So this is outside before loop here.
下面这些是在循环外的
We'll have the same four loops for each edge in our graph.
在图中对于每条边有同样的四个循环
We'll try to relax it. And if you can relax it,
我们将要松弛它  然后如果你们能够松弛它
the claim is that there has to be a negative weight cycle.
那就证明存在一个负权环
So this is the main thing that needs proof.
所以这就是我们所要求证的
OK, and that's the algorithm.
好吧  这就是这个算法
So the claim is that at the ends we should have d of v,
在结尾我们应该有d[v]
let's see, else so to speak.
接下来是“else”的情况
d of v equals delta of s comma v for every vertex, v.
对于每一个顶点v来说 d[v]=δ(s,v)
If we don't find a negative weight cycle according to this rule,
依据这条规则  如果我们没有找到负权环
that we should have all the shortest path weights.
我们就可以得到最短路径权值
That's the claim.
这就是这个观点
Now, the first question is, in here,
第一点是 在这里
the running time is very easy to analyze.
运行时间是非常容易分析的
So let's start with the running time.
所以从运行时间入手
We can compare it to Dijkstra,
我们能够将它和Dijkstra算法比较
which is over here.
在这里
What is the running time of this algorithm?
什么是算法的执行时间？
V times E, exactly.
V乘以E   一点没错
OK, I'm going to assume, because it's pretty reasonable,
好了  我来假定  这个很自然的
that V and E are both positive. Then it's V times E.
V和E都是正值  然后它就是V乘以E
So, this is a little bit slower, or a fair amount slower,
所以  这有一点的慢  不过可以接受
than Dijkstra's algorithm. There it is:
和Dijkstra的算法比起来  这些是
E plus V log V is essentially,
本质上是 (E + V)·log(V)
ignoring the logs, is pretty much linear time.
忽略这些log的话是线性时间
Here we have something that's at least quadratic in V,
在这里我们有一些是至少是二次的V
assuming your graph is connected.
假设你的图是连通图的话
So, it's slower,
所以 它会比较慢
but it's going to handle these negative weights.
但是它会解决这些负权值
Dijkstra can't handle negative weights at all.
Dijkstra算法完全都不能解决负权值
So, let's do an example,
那么我们举个例子
make it clear why you might hope this algorithm works.
让你们更加清楚为什么希望这个算法可以行得通
And then we'll prove that it works, of course.
然后我们当然将要证明这些是它行的通
But the proof will be pretty easy.
但是这些证明很简单
So, I'm going to draw a graph that has negative weights,
所以我要画一个有负权值的图
but no negative weight cycles
但是没有负权环
so that I get an interesting answer.
这样我可以得到了一个有趣的结果
Good. The other thing I need in order
很好  我们还要做一件事
to make the output of this algorithm well defined,
来解释这个算法的输出结果
it depends in which order you visit the edges.
它取决于你访问边的顺序
So I'm going to assign an arbitrary order to these edges.
所以我给这些边一个随机顺序
I could just ask you for an order,
其实你们随便说一个顺序就行
but to be consistent with the notes,
不过为了和笔记保持一致
I'll put an ordering on it.
我按这个顺序排列它
Let's say I put number four,
比如说我标注上4
say that's the fourth edge I'll visit.
表明这是我访问的第四条边
It doesn't matter.
其实这并不重要
But it will affect what happens
但它却会影响到
during the algorithm for a particular graph.
特定的图的运算过程
Do they get them all?
标完了么
One, two, three, four, five, six, seven, eight,
1 2 3 4 5 6 7 8
OK. And my source is going to be A.
好了  我的起始点是A
And, that's it. So, I want to run this algorithm.
然后  就是这样  我想要执行这个算法
I'm just going to initialize everything.
我就要进行初始化
So, I set the estimates for s to be zero,
那么  我设s的估值为0
and everyone else to be infinity.
然后剩下的每一个都是无穷大
And to give me some notion of time,
然后给我一些关于时间的概念
over here I'm going to draw or write down
在这里我画...或者说是写
what all of these d values are as the algorithm proceeds
当算法运行时所有这些d的值
because I'm going to start crossing them out and rewriting them
因为我要划掉并且重写它们
that the figure will get a little bit messier.
这个图会变得有点凌乱
But we can keep track of it over here.
我们在做个跟踪表
It's initially zero and infinities. Yeah?
这些是初始0还有无穷大的值  对吧？
[student] ……
[学生]：……
[Prof]:It doesn't matter. So, for the algorithm you can go
[教授]:其实没关系的  那么  对于这个算法 你可以
to the edges in a different order every time if you want.
按不同顺序来访问这些边
We'll prove that, but here I'm going to go
我们会证明的  但是现在我
through the same order every time.
每一次都用相同的顺序
Good question. It turns out it doesn't matter here.
问得好  实际上 在这里是没关系的
OK, so here's the starting point.
好吧  所以这里是起始点
Now I'm going to relax every edge.
现在我将要松弛每一条边
So, there's going to be a lot of edges here
所以  现在我们在这将有许多边
that don't do anything.
没有任何计算
I try to relax n minus one. I'd say, well,
我尝试去松弛N-1这条边  我想说
I know how to get from s to B with weight infinity.
我知道从S到B的的距离是无穷大
Infinity plus two I can get to from s to E.
那么无穷大加上2的话 我就能够从S到E
Well, infinity plus two is not much better than infinity.
好吧  无穷加上2并没有比无穷大很多
OK, so I don't do anything, don't update this to infinity.
好了  所以我什么都不做  不将这个更新为无穷
I mean, infinity plus two sounds even worse.
我想说  无穷大加上2听上去甚至更可怕
But infinity plus two is infinity.
但是无穷大加上2还是无穷大
OK, that's the edge number one.
好了  这是1号边
So, no relaxation edge number two,
所以  2号边不松弛
same deal as number three, same deal,
3号也是一样的
edge number four we start to get something interesting
4号边也是同样  我们开始得到一些有趣的东西
because I have a finite value here
因为我在这儿有一个有限的值
that says I can get from A to B
它说我从A到B
using a total weight of minus one. So that seems good.
只需要经过权值-1的边  所以这个看上去不错
I'll write down minus one here,
我在这里写下-1
and update B to minus one.
然后把B的值更新为-1
The rest stay the same. So, I'm just going to keep
剩下的保持一致  所以我只要坚持
doing this over and over. That was edge number four.
一遍一遍地做它  这是4号边
Number five, we also get a relaxation.
5号 我们也可以做一个松弛
Four is better than infinity.
4比无穷大更好
So, c gets a number of four.
所以  C是4
Then we get to edge number six.
然后我们到了6号边
That's infinity plus five is worse than four.
这是无穷大加上5 这比四差
OK, so no relaxation there.
好了  所以这儿没有松弛了
Edge number seven is interesting
7号边很有趣
because I have a finite value here minus one
因为我在这里有一个有限的值-1
plus the weight of this edge,
加上这条边的权值
which is three. That's a total of two,
权值为3   总数为2
which is actually better than four.
实际上比4好
So, this route, A, B, C is actually better
所以  这里的路线ABC实际上
than the route I just found a second ago.
比我之前找到的那个路线好
So, this is now a two.
所以  现在这是2
This is all happening in one iteration of the main loop.
这所有的都发生在一个主循环的迭代中
We actually found two good paths to C.
实际上我们发现了两条通向C的好路径
We found one better than the other.
我们发现其中一个比另一个好
OK, and that was edge number seven,
好了  这是7号边
and edge number eight is over here. It doesn't matter.
8号边在遥远的这边 它打了回酱油
OK, so that was round one of this outer loop,
好了  所以这是这个外层循环的第一个环路
so, the first value of I. i equals one.
所以  i的第一个值 i=1
OK, now we continue.
好了  现在我们继续
Just keep going. So, we start with edge number one.
继续这样  所以  我们从1号边开始
Now, minus one plus two is one.
现在-1加上2是1
That's better than infinity. It'll start speeding up.
比无穷大要好  我们要开始加速了
It's repetitive.
这都是重复的工作
It's actually not too much longer until we're done.
实际上直到我们做完了它也没有那么长
Number two, this is an infinity so we don't do anything.
2号  这是一个无穷大  所以我们不做任何事情
Number three: minus one plus two is one;
3号  -1加上2等于1
better than infinity.
比无穷大好
This is vertex d, and it's number three.
这是顶点d  然后它是3号
Number four we've already done. Nothing changed.
4号我们已经做完了  没有变化
Number five: this is where we see the path four again,
5号  这里我们又回到路径4
but that's worse than two. So, we don't update anything.
但是它比2差  所以我们不管它
Number six: one plus five is six,
6号  1加上5是6
which is bigger than two, so no good.
比2要大  所以不好
Go around this way. Number seven: same deal.
像这样绕一圈  7号也一样
Number eight is interesting.
8号很有趣
So, we have a weight of one here,
所以  我们这里的权值是1
a weight of minus three here.
这里的权值是-3
So, the total is minus two, which is better than one.
所以  总数是-2  比1要好
So, that was d. And, I believe that's it.
所以  这是d  然后  我相信它就是这样
So that was definitely the end of that round.
所以  这一轮一定结束了
So, it's i plus two
所以  i加上2
because we just looked at the eighth edge.
因为我们只看了第八条边
And, I'll cheat and check.
然后  我作弊看一下答案
Indeed, that is the last thing that happens.
真的  这就是最后一件要做的事
We can check the couple of outgoing edges from d
其实我们只需要检查从d向外的边
because that's the only one whose value just changed.
因为这是唯一被改变了的顶点
And, there are no more relaxations possible.
然后  这里没有更多可以松弛的了
So, that was in two rounds.
所以  这是在两圈内
The claim is we got all the shortest path weights.
我们就得到了所有的最短路径
The algorithm would actually
这个算法实际上会
loop four times to guarantee correctness
循环四圈来保证正确性
because we have five vertices here and one less than that.
因为我们这里有5个顶点  循环次数比它少1
So, in fact, in the execution here
所以  事实上  这个操作里
there are two more blank rounds at the bottom.
这下面还有两个空着没做的循环
Nothing happens. But, what the hell?
但已经不会再改变了 坑爹呢这是
OK, so that is Bellman-Ford.
好了 所以这就是Bellman-Ford算法了
I mean, it's certainly not doing anything wrong.
我的意思是 虽然它的确没有做错事
The question is, why is it guaranteed
但问题是  为什么它保证
to converge in V minus one steps
在v-1步内收敛（最短路径）
unless there is a negative weight cycle?
除非存在着负权环？
Question?
有问题么
[Prof]:Right, so that's an optimization.
[教授]:对  这是一个优化法
If you discover a whole round, and nothing happens,
如果你发现了整个循环 什么都没有发生
so you can keep track of that in the algorithm thing,
那么你可以把它记下来
you can stop. In the worst case,
然后停下来 但在最差的情况下
it won't make a difference. But in practice,
它不会有任何区别 但是在实际应用里
you probably want to do that. Yeah?
你可能希望这样做 对不？
Good question. All right, so some simple observations,
好问题  那么经过一些简单的观察
I mean, we're only doing relaxation.
我的意思是 我们只做松弛操作
So, we can use a lot of our analysis from before.
所以 我们可以用到之前的分析
In particular, the d values
特别是 d的数值
are only decreasing monotonically.
只单调递减
As we cross out values here,
当我们在这里划去了一些数值
we are always making it smaller, which is good.
我们总是将它变小 这是好的
Another nifty thing about this algorithm is that
这算法的另一个优点是
you can run it even in a distributed system.
你甚至可以在分布式计算机系统下运行它
If this is some actual network, some computer network,
如果这是一些真是的网络,一些电脑网络
and these are machines,
然后这些是机器
and they're communicating by these links,
它们之间用这些线连接
I mean, it's a purely local thing.
我的意思是 这种操作纯粹的局部的
Relaxation is a local thing.
松弛是局部的
You don't need any global strategy,
你们不需要任何的整体策略
and you're asking about,
你们如果问
can we do a different order in each step?
我们可以在每一步做一个不同的顺序么？
Well, yeah, you could just keep relaxing edges,
我说可以啊 你可以继续松弛边缘
and keep relaxing edges,
继续松弛边缘
and just keep going for the entire lifetime of the network.
然后在你分布式网络中一直做这个
And eventually, you will find shortest paths.
最终 你将找到最短路径
So, this algorithm is guaranteed to finish in V rounds
所以 这个算法保证在V循环内完成
in a distributed system. It might be more asynchronous.
在分布式系统里  它可能更加不同步
And, it's a little harder to analyze.
而且 分析起来会更难一些
But it will still work eventually.
但是这么做行得通
It's guaranteed to converge.
它保证是收敛
And so, Bellman-Ford is used
所以 Bellman-ford算法
a lot in the Internet for finding shortest paths.
经常用于求网络上的最短路径问题
OK, so let's finally prove that it works.
好了 所以最后让我们证明它会有效吧
This should only take a couple of boards.
这应该用几块黑板就能讲完
So let's suppose we have a graph and some edge weights
假设我们有一个图和一些边权值
that have no negative weight cycles.
没有负权环
Then the claim is that
然后这个观点是
we terminate with the correct answer.
我们最终会得到正确答案
So, Bellman-Ford terminates with all of these
所以 当Bellman-ford算法结束时
d of v values set to the delta values for every vertex.
所有顶点的d[v]都会等于δ值（最短路径值）
OK, the proof is going to be pretty immediate
证明将变得十分直接
using lemmas that we had from before if you remember them
只要用到这些之前讲的引理    还记得吧？
So, we're just going to look at every vertex separately.
所以 我们只是分开的观察每一个顶点
So, I'll call the vertex v.
所以 我叫这个顶点V
The claim is that this holds by the end of the algorithm.
这个在算法结束之前都是成立的
So, remember what we need to prove is that at some point,
所以 记得我们需要证明的是在某一时间点
d of v equals delta of s comma v
d[v]=δ(s,v)
because we know it decreases monotonically,
因为我们知道它单调递减
and we know that it never gets
并且我们知道它不会
any smaller than the correct value
变得比正确值还小
because relaxations are always safe.
因为松弛永远是安全的
So, we just need to show at some point this holds,
所以我们只需证明 在某一时间点它是成立的
and that it will hold at the end.
那么它到最后都一直会是成立的
So, by monotonicity of the d values,
所以  通过d值的单调性
and by correctness part one,
和已经证明了的第一条正确性
which was that the d of v's
就是d[v]
are always greater than or equal to the deltas,
总是大于等于δ
we only need to show that at some point we have equality.
我们只需要证明在某一时间点 等式成立
So that's our goal.
这就是我们的目的
So what we're going to do is just look at v,
那么 我们将要做的只是观察V
and the shortest path to v,
和到V的最短路径
and see what happens to the algorithm relative to that path.
然后我们观察 这条路径上的算法做了什么
So, I'm going to name the path. Let's call it p.
所以 我来给这条路径起个名字 我们叫它p
It starts at vertex v_0 and goes to v_1, v_2,
它从顶点v_0开始然后转向v_1 v_2
whatever, and ends at v_k.
然后 在v_k停止
And, this is not just any shortest path,
这不仅仅是最短途径而已
but it's one that starts at s.
它是从s开始的
So, v_0's s, and it ends at v.
所以 v_0是s 并且在v终止
So, I'm going to give a couple of names to s and v
所以我要给s和v起几个名字
so I can talk about the path more uniformly.
这样讨论起来才能保持一致
So, this is a shortest path from s to v.
所以 这是从s到v的最短路径
Now, I also want it to be
现在 我同样想要它
not just any shortest path from s to v,
不只是从s到v的任何的最短路径
but among all shortest paths from s to v
而且在所有s到v里的最短路径之间
I want it to be one with the fewest possible edges.
经过最少的边的那一条最短路径
OK, so shortest here means
好了 最短在这里意味着
in terms of the total weight of the path.
用路径的总权值表示
Subject to being shortest in weight,
先要满足权重最小
I want it to also be shortest in the number of edges.
而且它经过的边的数目里也是最少的
And, the reason I want that is to be able to conclude
然后 它这么做的原因是 这样能够推导出
that p is a simple path,
p是一个简单路径
meaning that it doesn't repeat any vertices.
意味着它没有任何重复的顶点
Now, can anyone tell me why I need to assume
现在 有谁可以告诉我为什么我需要假定
that the number of edges is the smallest possible
边的数量是能尽可能少的
in order to guarantee that p is simple? The claim is that
来保证p是最简的？ 我们说
not all shortest paths are necessarily simple. Yeah?
不是所有的最短路径都必须是简单的  对么
[Student]：……
[学生]：……
[Prof]:Right, I can have a zero weight cycle, exactly.
[教授]:是的 我可能有一个零权环  确实是
So, we are hoping, I mean, in fact in the theorem here,
所以 我的意思是 我们事实上都希望在这个定理里
we're assuming that there are no negative weight cycles.
我们假设这里没有负权环
But there might be zero weight cycles still.
但是这里可能仍旧有零权环
As a zero weight cycle, you can put that in the middle
作为一个零权环,你可以将它放进任何一个最短路径之间
of any shortest path to make it arbitrarily long,
使路径变得任意地长
repeat vertices over and over.
一遍遍地重复经过这些点
That's going to be annoying.
这样很蛋疼啊
What I want is that p is simple.
我想要的p是简单路径
And, I can guarantee that essentially by shortcutting.
其实有个捷径可以保证
If ever I take a zero weight cycle, I throw it away.
每当我遇到一个零权环  我就把它扔掉
And this is one mathematical way of doing that.
然后这是它的数学语言表达
OK, now what else do we know about this shortest path?
好了 现在关于这个最短路径我们知道些什么？
We know that subpaths of shortest paths are shortest paths
我们知道  最短路径的子路径是最短路径
That's optimal substructure.
这是一个最优子结构
So, we know what the shortest path from s to v_i
所以 我们知道了从s到v_i的最短路径
is sort of inductively. It's the shortest path,
有点归纳法的感觉   这个是最短路径
I mean, it's the weight of that path, which is,
我的意思是  它是那条路径的权值
in particular, the shortest path from s to v_i
特别是从s到v_(i-1)的最短途径
minus one plus the weight of the last edge,
加上最后一条边的权值
v_i minus one to v_i.
v_(i-1)到v_i
So, this is by optimal substructure as we proved last time.
所以 这是我们上次通过最优子结构所证明的
OK, and I think that's pretty much the warm-up.
好了 想这已经足够热身了
So, I want to sort of do this inductively in i,
我现在要用i来做归纳法
start out with v zero, and go up to v_k.
从v_0开始进行   然后一直到v_k
So, the first question is,
所以 第一个问题是
what is d of v_0, which is s?
d[v_0]是什么  也就是s？
What is d of the source?
源点的d值是多少？
Well, certainly at the beginning of the algorithm,
好吧 当然在这个算法的开始
it's zero.
它是零
So, let's say equals zero initially
所以 让我们说起初等于零
because that's what we set it to.
因为这是我们对它赋值的
And it only goes down from there.
然后它只从这里下降
So, it certainly, at most, zero.
所以 它无疑的 不超过零
The real question is, what is delta of s comma v_0.
这真正的问题是 什么是δ(s,v_0)
What is the shortest path weight from s to s?
什么是从s到s的最短路径
It has to be zero,
它必须为零
otherwise you have a negative weight cycle, exactly.
否则你们会有个负权环   对
My favorite answer, zero.
我最喜欢的答案 零
So, if we had another path from s to s,
那么  如果我们有另一条从s到s的路径
I mean, that is a cycle.
我的意思是 那是一个回路
So, it's got to be zero. So, these are actually equal
所以它应该是零  所以  这里实际上
at the beginning of the algorithm, which is great.
在算法开始相等  这个灰常不错
That means they will be for all time
这意味着它会一直都是这样
because we just argued up here, only goes down,
因为我们刚刚这里讨论过  它一直变小
never can get too small.
永远不会变得过小
So, we have d of v_0 set to the right thing.
所以d[v_0]的值设对了
good for the base case of the induction.
对归纳法的基础情况来说很好
Of course, what we really care about is v_k,
当然 我们真正关心的是v_k
which is v. So, let's talk about the v_i inductively,
就是v  那么让我们用归纳法求一下v_i
and then we will get v_k as a result.
之后我们会得到一个结果v_k
So, yeah, let's do it by induction.
那么  让我们用归纳法来做
That's more fun. Let's say that d of v_i
这更有趣   我们说
is equal to delta of s v_i
d[Vi] =δ(s, v_i)
after i rounds of the algorithm.
在循环了i次这个算法以后
So, this is actually referring to the i
所以实际上这个涉及到了i
that is in the algorithm here. These are rounds.
在这个算法里  它们是循环次数
So, one round is an entire execution of all the edges,
一个循环执行了所有的边
relaxation of all the edges.
对所有边进行松弛
So, this is certainly true for i equals zero.
所以i等于零无疑是正确的
We just proved that. After zero rounds,
我们刚证明过了  在零圈过后
at the beginning of the algorithm,
在算法开始的阶段
d of v_0 equals delta of s, v_0.
d[v_0] = δ(s,v_0)
OK, so now, that's not really what I wanted, but OK, fine.
好了  那么现在  这并不是我真的想要的  不过就这样吧
Now we'll prove it for d of v_i plus one.
现在我们将要证明d[v_(i+1)]的情况
Generally, I recommend you assume something.
我建议你们做一些假设
In fact, why don't I follow my own advice and change it?
其实... 为什么不按照我说的来改掉它
It's usually nicer to think of induction as recursion.
通常把归纳法想成递归会比较好
So, you assume that this is true, let's say,
假设这个成立  我们说
for j less than the i that you care about,
你们关心的  j比i小的时候
and then you prove it for d of v_i.
然后你们d[v_i]成立
It's usually a lot easier to think about it that way.
这样想通常要简单得多
In particular, you can use
特别是  你可以用
strong induction for all j less than i.
完整归纳法证明所有j比i小时的情况
Here, we're only going to need it for one less.
这里我们只需要小于的情况
We have some relation between i and i minus one here
我们在这里有一些在i和i-1之间的联系
in terms of the deltas.
用δ表示
And so, we want to argue something about the d values.
我们要讨论一下d值
OK, well, let's think about what's going on here.
好  我们来想想 接下来这里会发生什么
We know that, let's say, after i minus one rounds,
我们知道  这样说  在i-1圈后
we have this inductive hypothesis,
我们有了这个归纳假设
d of v_i minus one equals delta of s v_i minus one.
d[v_(i-1)]=δ(s,v_(i-1))
And, we want to conclude that after i rounds,
然后我们要推断i圈之后
so we have one more round to do this.
那么我们有多了一轮来做这个
We want to conclude that d of v_i has the right answer,
我们想要推断d[v_i]有正确的解
delta of s comma v_i. Does that look familiar at all?
δ(S,Vi)    它们是不是很眼熟？
So we want to relax every edge in this round.
我们要在这一轮里松弛每一条边
In particular, at some point,
特别是  在某些点
we have to relax the edge from v_i minus one to v_i.
我们必须松弛从v_(i-1)到v_i的边
We know that this path consists of edges.
我们知道边组成了这条路径
That's the definition of a path.
这是关于路径的定义
So, during the i'th round, we relax every edge.
在第i轮的时候  我们松弛了每一条边
So, we better relax v_i minus one v_i.
所以 我们也会松弛到（v_(i-1),v_i)
And, what happens then? It's a test of memory.
那么接下来发生了什么  这是一个记忆测试
Quick, the Death Star is approaching.
速度点   死星正在逼近
So, if we have the correct value for v_i minus one,
所以  如果我们给v_(i-1)取得了一个正确的值
that we relax an outgoing edge from there,
我们松弛了一条从这里向外的边
and that edge is an edge of the shortest path from s to v_i.
而这条边是从s到v_i的最短路径中的一段
What do we know? d of v_i becomes the correct value,
那么我们知道了什么？ d[v_i]变成了正确的值
delta of s comma v_i.
δ(S, Vi)
This was called correctness lemma last time.
上次我们叫它正确性引理
One of the things we proved about Dijkstra's algorithm,
讲Dijkstra算法时我们证明过
but it was really just a fact about relaxation.
但是它实际上只是个松弛操作
And it was a pretty simple proof.
很容易证明
And it comes from this fact.
它是从这来的
We know the shortest path weight is this.
我们知道最短路径权值是这个
So, certainly d of v_i was at least this big,
所以  理所当然的 d[v_i]至少是这么大
and let's suppose it's greater, or otherwise we were done.
我们假设它还要大一点  否则就已经做完了
We know d of v_i minus one is set to this.
我们设了v_(i-1)的值是这个
And so, this is exactly the condition
所以 无疑这就是
that's being checked in the relaxation step.
在松弛操作里被检验的条件
And, the d of v_i value will be
然后  假设d[v_i]的值将会
greater than this, let's suppose.
比这个大 这么假定的话
And then, we'll set it equal to this.
然后我们设它等于这个
And that's exactly d of s, v_i.
准确来说就是d(s,v_i)
So, when we relax that edge,
所以 当我们松弛那条边
we've got to set it to the right value.
我们给了它一个正确的数值
So, this is the end of the proof, right?
那么证明就完成了  对吧
It's very simple. The point is,
这很简单  关键是
you look at your shortest path. Here it is.
看下你的最短路径  在这里
And if we assume there's no negative weight cycles,
然后如果我们假设这里没有负权环
this has the correct value initially.
在最初有正确的值
d of s is going to be zero. After the first round,
d[s]将会变成零  在第一轮过后
you've got to relax this edge.
你肯定会松弛这条边
And then you get the right value for that vertex.
然后你得到了那个顶点的正确数值
After the second round, you've got to relax this edge,
在第二轮之后  你肯定松弛这条边
which gets you the right d value
在这里你得到了这个顶点的
for this vertex and so on.
正确d值  等等等等
And so, no matter which shortest path you take,
所以  无论你选择了哪一条最短路径
you can apply this analysis.
你可以运用这个分析
And you know that by, if the length of this path,
然后你知道 如果这条路径的长度
here we assumed it was k edges,
在这里我们假设它是k条边
then after k rounds you've got to be done.
然后在k轮之后  你就完成了
OK, so this was not actually the end of the proof.
好吧其实还没证完
Sorry. So this means after k rounds,
不好意思  所以这意味着在k轮之后
we have the right answer for v_k, which is v.
v_k就有一个正确的值  就是v
So, the only question is how big could k be?
所以唯一的问题就是k可以变成多大
And, it better be the right answer, at most,
最好是正确答案  最大的情况
v minus one is the claim by the algorithm
是v-1  通过算法证明
that you only need to do v minus one steps.
你只需要做v-1步
And indeed, the number of edges
确实  边的数量
in a simple path in a graph is,
在简单路径的图里
at most, the number of vertices minus one.
顶多是顶点的数量减一
k is, at most, v minus one because p is simple.
k最多是v-1  因为p是简单路径
So, that's why we had to assume that
所以这就是为什么我们要假设
it wasn't just any shortest path.
它不止是任何的最短路径
It had to be a simple one so it didn't repeat any vertices.
它必须是一个简单路径  不用重复任何的顶点
So there are, at most, V vertices in the path,
所以在这条路径里最多有V个顶点
so at most, V minus one edges in the path.
所以在这个路径里最多有v-1条边
OK, and that's all there is to Bellman-Ford.
好了  这就是Bellman-ford算法
pretty simple in correctness.
在正确性上检验上十分简单
Of course, we're using a lot
当然我们用了很多
of the lemmas that we proved last time,
上次证明过的定理
which makes it easier. OK, a consequence of this theorem,
来使它变得简单  好  这套理论的结果
or of this proof is that if Bellman-Ford fails to converge,
或这个证明的结果是   如果Bellman-ford算法不能收敛
and that's what the algorithm is checking
就是这个算法正在检验的
is whether this relaxation
就是检验这个松弛是否
still requires work after these d minus one steps.
在d-1步之后还要继续算
Right, the end of this algorithm
对  在这个算法末尾
is run another round, a V'th round,
还有一轮  就是第V轮
see whether anything changes.
我们来看看是否有任何改变
So, we'll say that the algorithm
我们假设  这个算法
fails to converge after V minus one steps or rounds.
在v-1轮操作后不收敛
Then, there has to be a negative weight cycle.
那么这里肯定有一个负权环
OK, this is just a contrapositive of what we proved.
这个只是一个我们刚刚证明的命题的逆否命题
We proved that if you assume
我们证明了  如果假设
there's no negative weight cycle,
这里没有负权环
then we know that d of s is zero,
那么d[s]为零
and then all this argument says
然后所有这些论证都在说
is you've got to converge after v minus one rounds.
在v-1圈之后会收敛
There can't be anything left to do
那就没什么好做的了
once you've reached the shortest path weights
一旦你达到了最短路径权值
because you're going monotonically;
因为你是单调递减的
you can never hit the bottom.
你又不能突破最小值
You can never go through the floor.
你又不能捅破地板
So, if you fail to converge somehow
所以  如果你无论什么原因收敛失败了
after V minus one rounds,
在v-1轮后
you've got to have violated the assumption.
你肯定是违反了假设
The only assumption we made
我们所作出的唯一的假设
was there's no negative weight cycle.
是这里没有负权环
So, this tells us that Bellman-Ford is actually correct.
所以这告诉我们 Bellman-ford算法实际上是对的
When it says that there is a negative weight cycle,
当它说这里有负权环
it indeed means it.
那就真的是有
It's true. OK, and you can modify Bellman-Ford
这是对的  好吧  你可以调整Bellman-ford算法
in that case to sort of run a little longer,
在那种情况下稍稍运行久一些
and find where all the minus infinities are.
然后把所有的负无穷点找出来
And that is, in some sense,
这个  在某种意义上
one of the things you have to do in your problem set,
是在你习题集里要做的
I believe. So, I won't cover it here.
所以这里就不讲了
But, it's a good exercise in any case to figure out
但是这绝对是一个很好的练习
how you would find where the minus infinities are.
来想出方法找到负无穷
What are all the vertices reachable
哪些是迷失在了
from negative weight cycle?
负权环里的顶点？
Those are the ones that have minus infinities.
那些负无穷的顶点就是了
OK, so you might say, well, that was awfully fast.
好   你可能会说我讲得太快了
Actually, it's not over yet.
实际上还没完
The episode is not yet ended.
这集还没完
We're going to use Bellman-Ford
我们要用到Bellman-ford算法
to solve the even bigger and greater shortest path problems.
来解决甚至更大更复杂的最短路径问题
And in the remainder of today's lecture,
然后在今天的讲座的剩下部分
we will see it applied to a more general problem,
我们还将看到它应用于更加普遍的问题
in some sense, called linear programming.
在某种程度上  我们叫它线性规划
And the next lecture,
在接下来的讲座里
we'll really use it to do some amazing stuff
我们将用它来做一些神奇的东西
with all pairs shortest paths. Let's go over here.
用于全对最短路径  我们从这开始讲
So, our goal, although it won't be obvious today,
我们的目标是——虽然今天不是很看得出来
is to be able to compute the
是能够计算出
shortest paths between every pair of vertices,
每对顶点之间的最短路径
which we could certainly do
我们现在只需
at this point just by running Bellman-Ford v times.
运行Bellman-ford算法v次
OK, but we want to do better than that, of course.
但是我们当然要比这个做得更好
And, that will be the climax of the trilogy.
接下来是整个三部曲的高潮
OK, today we just discovered who Luke's father is.
今天我们刚刚发现了卢克的爸爸是谁
So, it turns out the father
那么 我们发现这个
of shortest paths is linear programming.
最短途径的的父亲是线性规划
Actually, simultaneously the father and the mother
实际上  它既是父亲又是母亲
because programs do not have gender.
因为程序没有性别 = =
OK, my father likes to say,
好吧  我父亲喜欢说
we both took improv comedy lessons
我们都去学了即兴演讲
so we have degrees in improvisation.
所以我们有即兴创作的学位
And he said, you know, we went to improve classes
然后他说  你知道  我们去即兴演讲课
in order to learn how to make our humor better.
是为了让我们的段子更幽默
And, the problem is,
但问题是
it didn't actually make our humor better.
实际上它并没有让我们更幽默
It just made us less afraid to use it.
它只是让我们滥用冷笑话而已
So, you are subjected to all this improv humor.
所以说 你们都被我冷到了
I didn't see the connection of Luke's father,
其实任何这和卢克父亲半毛钱关系都没有
but there you go. OK, so, linear programming
总之我们继续  好吧  线性规划
is a very general problem, a very big tool.
是非常典型的问题  一个强大的工具
Has anyone seen linear programming before?
有没有任何人在此之前知道线性规划
OK, one person. And, I'm sure you will,
好吧  有一个  然后  我确定你这辈子
at some time in your life,
某个时候会碰到
do anything vaguely computing optimization related,
做一些像是最优化的计算
linear programming comes up at some point.
这就是某种线性规划
It's a very useful tool.
是一个非常有用的工具
You're given a matrix and two vectors:
现在给你一个矩阵和两个向量
not too exciting yet.
还不够令人兴奋
What you want to do is find a vector.
你所想要做的就是找到一个向量
This is a very dry description.
这是一个相当没劲的解释
We'll see what makes it so interesting in a moment.
我们会看到是什么马上让它变得有趣
So, you want to maximize some objective,
所以  你想要把一些目标函数最大化
and you have some constraints. And they're all linear.
你有一些约束条件  它们都是用线性式表示的
So, the objective is a linear function in the variables x,
所以  目标函数是含x的线性函数
and your constraints are a bunch of linear constraints,
然后你的约束条件是一连串的线性式
inequality constraints, that's one makes an interesting.
不等式的约束  这是一个让它变得有趣的东西
It's not just solving a linear system
这不仅仅是解线性方程组
as you've seen in linear algebra, or whatever.
这不仅仅是算线性代数神马的
Or, of course, it could be that there is no such x.
或者  当然它也可能没有这样的x
OK, vaguely familiar you might think
好了  是不是觉得跟Bellman-ford
to the theorem about Bellman-Ford.
有些千丝万缕的联系
And we'll show that there's some kind of connection here
我们会看到它们之间的一些联系
that either you want to find something,
要么你想要发现些什么
or show that it doesn't exist.
或者说明它不存在
Well, that's still a pretty vague connection,
好了  这仍旧是一个很模糊的联系
but I also want to maximize something,
但我同样想要最大化一些东西
or sort of minimize the shortest paths,
或者最小化最短路径
OK, somewhat similar. We have these constraints.
之类的东东  我们有这些约束
So, yeah. This may be intuitive to you,
可能对你来说很直观
I don't know. I prefer a more geometric picture,
差不多吧  我更偏向于几何的图
and I will try to draw such a geometric picture,
然后我试着画个几何图出来
and I've never tried to do this on a blackboard,
我从来没有试过在黑板上做这个
so it should be interesting.
应该很好玩
I think I'm going to fail miserably.
我想我将要坑爹地失败了
It sort of looks like a dodecahedron, right?
它看起来神似个十二面体
Sort of, kind of, not really.
嘛 差不多吧 好吧不像
A bit rough on the bottom, OK.
底下不平  好吧
So, if you have a bunch of linear constraints,
所以 如果你有一连串的线性约束
this is supposed to be in 3-D. Now I labeled it.
这个应该是三维的  我现在标出来
It's now in 3-D. Good.
它在三维中  很好
So, you have these linear constraints.
所以 你有这些线性约束
That turns out to define hyperplanes in n dimensions.
我们想到用它们来定义n维里的超平面
OK, so you have a space here
好了  这里你们有了一个空间
that's three-dimensional space.
这是三维空间
So, n equals three. And, these hyperplanes,
所以  n等于3  然后  这些超平面
if you're looking at one side of the hyperplane,
如果从超平面的一面看过去
that's the less than or equal to,
这是小于或等于
if you take the intersection,
如果你取交叉点
you get some convex polytope or polyhedron.
你会得到一些凸多面体或者多面体
In 3-D, you might get a dodecahedron or whatever.
在三维里你可能得到一个十二面体什么的
And, your goal, you have some objective vector c,
然后你的目标  你有一些目标向量c
let's say, up.
我们说  方向向上
Suppose that's the c vector.
假设这是向量c
Your goal is to find the highest point in this polytope.
你的目标是找到这个多面体的最高点
So here, it's maybe this one. OK, this is the target.
所以在这里  可能是这个  好了  这个是目标
This is the optimal, x.
这是最优点x
That is the geometric view.
这是从几何的角度来说
If you prefer the algebraic view,
如果你用代数来看
you want to maximize the c transpose times x.
你想要使c的转置乘x最大化
So, this is m. This is n.
所以  这个是m  这个是n
Check out the dimensions work out.
检验维度是对的
So that's saying you want to maximize the dot product.
所以 这就是说你想要最大化点乘积
You want to maximize the extent
你想要增大
to which x is in the direction c.
x在c方向上的长度
And, you want to maximize that subject to some constraints,
然后  你想要使它最大化  在某些限制条件下
which looks something like this, maybe.
看上去可能有点像这个
So, this is A, and it's m by n.
所以   这是A   这个是m排n列
You want to multiply it by,
你想要把它乘以……
it should be something of height n.
某些有n排的的东西
That's x. Let me put x down here, n by one.
这就是x  把x写下来  n排1列
And, it should be less than
然后 它应该小于
or equal to something of this height, which is B,
或等于一些高度是这个的  这个是B
the right hand side. OK, that's the algebraic view,
在符号右边  好的  这就是从代数角度看
just to check out all the dimensions are working out.
检验下所有维度都弄对了
But, you can read these off in each row here,
不过你可以这样一行一行下来
when multiplied by this column, gives you one value here.
和这一列相乘  然后得出来的是这里这个数
And as just a linear constraints on all the x sides.
仅仅是作为所有x这边的一个线性约束
Next, you want to maximize this particular linear function
接下来你想要最大化这个具体的线性函数
of x_1 up to x_n subject to these constraints, OK
从x_1到x_n  来满足这些约束
Pretty simple, but pretty powerful in general.
十分简单  但是很牛逼
So, it turns out that with, you can formulate a huge number
你可以把各种各样的问题
of problems such as shortest paths as a linear program.
用线性规划的方法解决 例如最短路径问题
So, it's a general tool. And in this class,
所以  这是一个经典的工具  在这堂课里
we will not cover any algorithms
我们将不涉及任何的算法
for solving linear programming.
来解决线性规划
It's a bit tricky.
这有一点狡猾
I'll just mention that they are out there.
我只提一下它们的存在
So, there's many efficient algorithms,
有许多高效的算法
and lots of code that does this.
和很多的代码来做这个
It's a very practical setup.
这是一个非常实用的方案
So, lots of algorithms to solve LP's, linear programs.
所以  许多的算法来解决线性规划问题
Linear programming is usually called LP.
线性规划通常被称作LP
And, I'll mention a few of them.
我会举些例子
There's the simplex algorithm. This is one of the first.
有个叫单一算法  这个是最早的之一
I think it is the first, the ellipsoid algorithm.
我想它是第一个  椭球算法
There's interior point methods,
还有个内点法
and there's random sampling.
还有随机抽样
I'll just say a little bit about each of these
这里每个我就讲一点点
because we're not going to talk about any of them in depth.
因为我们不会去深度地讨论任何一个
The simplex algorithm, this is, I mean,
我所指的单一算法
one of the first algorithms in the world in some sense,
某种程度上可以说是世界上出现的最早的算法之一
certainly one of the most popular. It's still used today
也无疑是最普遍的算法之一  一直沿用至今
Almost all linear programming code
几乎所有的线性规划代码
uses the simplex algorithm.
都在用单一算法
It happens to run an exponential time in the worst-case,
它碰巧在最坏情况里运行次数呈指数增长
so it's actually pretty bad theoretically.
所以理论上 它其实是很烂的
But in practice, it works really well.
但是在实际运用中  它的效果很好
And there is some recent work
然后最近有一些研究
that tries to understand this.
是来尝试着理解这个的
It's still exponential in the worst case.
它还是在最坏情况下运行次数呈指数增长
But, it's practical. There's actually an open problem
但是  它很实用  实际上这里有一个有争议的问题
whether there exists a variation of simplex
就是是否存在单一算法的变种
that runs in polynomial time. But, I won't go into that.
能在多项式时间内运行  这里我就不讲了
That's a major open problem
这是一个主要的争议问题
in this area of linear programming.
在这个线性规划的领域里
The ellipsoid algorithm was the first algorithm
这个椭球算法是第一个
to solve linear programming in polynomial time.
用来解决多项式时间的线性规划的算法
So for a long time, people didn't know. Around this time
所以  在很长一段时间里 人们不知道  在那段时间
people started realizing polynomial time is a good thing.
人们开始意识到多项式时间是个好东西
That happened around the late 60s.
这大概是在60年代后期
Polynomial time is good.
多项式时间是个好东西
And, the ellipsoid algorithm is the first one to do it.
椭球算法是第一个这么做的
It's a very general algorithm, and very powerful,
这是一个非常普遍的算法  并且非常的有效
theoretically, completely impractical. But, it's cool.
理论上来说  但完全不实用  不过它很酷炫
It lets you do things like you can solve a linear program
它让你做一些事情  像是你可以在多项式时间内
that has exponentially many constraints in polynomial time.
解决一个有指数多个约束的线性规划
You've got all sorts of crazy things.
你可以得到各种各样的疯狂的东西
So, I'll just say it's polynomial time.
所以 我只会说它是多项式时间
I can't say something nice about it;
我真的说不出什么好话了
don't say it at all. It's impractical.
但我们不说它  它很不实用
Interior point methods are sort of the mixture.
内点法类似是一种混合
They run in polynomial time. You can guarantee that.
它们在多项式时间里运行  这个可以保证
And, they are also pretty practical,
然后  它们也同样很实用
and there's sort of this competition these days
这些天有些这样的争论
about whether simplex or interior point is better.
关于单一算法和内点法哪个更好
And, I don't know what it is today
不知道今天是怎样
but a few years ago they were neck and neck.
但是在几年前它们是并驾齐驱的
And, random sampling is a brand new approach.
而且随即抽样是一个全新的方式
This is just from a couple years ago by two MIT professors,
这是几年前两个MIT教授
Dimitris Bertsimas and Santosh Vempala,
Dimitris Bertsimas 和 Santosh Vempala搞的
One in EE, I guess the other is in applied math.
一个搞电子工程的 我猜另一个是教应用数学的
So, just to show you,
所以 只是为了告诉你们
there's active work in this area.
这个领域相当活跃
People are still finding new ways to solve linear programs.
人们仍旧在寻找新的方法来解决线性规划
This is completely randomized, and very simple,
这完全是随机的  并且十分简单
and very general. It hasn't been implemented,
十分普通  它还没有被运用
so we don't know how practical it is yet.
所以 我们还不知道它是否实用
But, it has potential. OK pretty neat.
但是  它有潜力  好的就这么多了
OK, we're going to look at
我们继续看
a somewhat simpler version of linear programming.
一个稍微简单一点的线性规划
The first restriction we are going to make
我们要去做的第一个限制
is actually not much of a restriction.
实际上并不是一个限制
But, nonetheless we will consider it,
但是虽然如此  我们还是会考虑它
it's a little bit easier to think about. So here,
它比较容易弄懂  所以在这里
we had some polytope we wanted to maximize some objective.
我们有一些多面体 我们想要把一些目标最大化
In a feasibility problem, I just want to know,
在可行性问题上 我只想知道
is the polytope empty?
多面体是不是空的
Can you find any point in that polytope?
你能找到在多面体里的任何一个点吗？
Can you find any set of values, x,
你能找到任何一系列的x值
that satisfy these constraints?
来满足那些约束吗？
OK, so there's no objective c.
好了 所以这里没有目标函数c
just find x such that AX is less than or equal to B.
只要找到x  使得Ax小于等于B就好
OK, it turns out you can prove a very general theorem
好了 结论是你可以证明一个非常普遍的理论
that if you can solve linear feasibility,
如果你可以解决线性可行性
you can also solve linear programming.
那你也能够解决线性规划
We won't prove that here, but this is actually no easier
我们不会在这里证明这点  但是实际上它并不比
than the original problem even though it feels easier,
原来的问题简单  即使它感觉起来更简单
and it's easier to think about.
而且考虑起来也很容易
I was just saying actually no easier than LP.
我只是说实际上它不比线性规划简单
OK, the next restriction we're going to make
好了  我们下一个要做的限制
is a real restriction.
是个真正的限制条件
And it simplifies the problem quite a bit.
它使这个问题简化了很多
And that's to look at different constraints.
而且是用在不同的约束条件下
And, if all this seemed a bit abstract so far,
如果这些现在看上去有那么点的抽象
we will now ground ourselves little bit.
我们现在来点预备知识
A system of different constraints
一个有不同约束的系统
is a linear feasibility problem.
是一个线性的可行性问题
So, it's an LP where there's no objective.
所以 这是一个没有目标的线性规划
And, it's with a restriction,
并且带有一个限制
so, where each row of the matrix, so, the matrix A
矩阵每行  呃  在矩阵A里
has one one, and it has one minus one,
有一个1   还有一个 -1
and everything else in the row is zero.
剩下的在那行里的每一个都是零
OK, in other words, each constraint
好了  换句话说  每一个约束
has its very simple form.
有它很简单的形式
It involves two variables and some number.
它涉及了两个变量和一些数
So, we have something like x_j minus x_i
所以 我们有了一些像x_j - x_i
is less than or equal to w_ij.
小于等于W_ij
So, this is just a number. These are two variables.
所以 这仅仅是个数字 它们是两个变量
There's a minus sign, no values up here,
这里有个一个减号 这里没有其他值
no coefficients, no other of the X_k's appear,
没有系数 没有其他的x_k出现
just two of them. And, you have a bunch of
只有它们两个 然后你有了一连串的
constraints of this form, one per row of the matrix.
这种形式的约束条件  矩阵里每一行一个
Geometrically, I haven't thought about what this means.
我还没想过它的几何意义
I think it means the hyperplanes are pretty simple.
我想这意味着超平面都很简单
Sorry I can't do better than that.
不好意思我也不知道了
It's a little hard to see this in high dimensions.
在多维里想象这个有点难
But, it will start to correspond to something we've seen,
但是 它开始和我们之前见过的东西联系起来
namely the board that its next to, very shortly.
也就是说和旁边这块黑板  很快了
OK, so let's do a very quick example
好  现在我很快地举些例子
mainly to have something to point at.
大致说明一下
Here's a very simple system of difference constraints --
这儿是个非常简单的 不同约束组成的式组
OK, and a solution. Why not?
和一个解  为什么不呢
It's not totally trivial to solve this,
解决它并不是特别繁琐
but here's a solution.
但这里有解
And the only thing to check is that
唯一要去检查的是
each of these constraints is satisfied.
每一个这里的约束都被满足了
x_1 minus x_2 is three,
x_1-x_2是3
which is less than or equal to three, and so on.
小于等于三 等等
There could be negative values.
这里可能有一个负值
There could be positive values. It doesn't matter.
也可能有一个正值  都可以
I'd like to transform this system
我现在想把这个
of difference constraints into a graph
有不同约束的式组变成一张图
because we know a lot about graphs.
因为我们知道很多关于图的东西
So, we're going to call this the constraint graph.
所以 我们把这个叫做约束图
And, it's going to represent these constraints.
然后 它将代表这些约束
How'd I do it? Well, I take every constraint,
我要怎么做？ 我把每一个约束
which in general looks like this,
总之看上去是这样
and I convert it into an edge.
然后我把它看成一条边
OK, so if I write it as x_j minus x_i
好了 所以如果我写它是x_j - x_i
is less than or equal to some w_ij,
小于等于W_ji
w seems suggestive of weights.
w一看就知道是指权值
That's exactly why I called it w.
准确来说这就是我们叫它w的原因
I'm going to make that an edge from v_i to v_j.
我要让它成为从v_i到v_j的一条边
So, the order flips a little bit.
顺序有点不一样
And, the weight of that edge is w_ij.
那条边的权值是W_ij
So, just do that. Make n vertices.
所以 只要这么做 做出n个顶点
So, you have the number of vertices equals n.
那么就得出顶点数等于n
The number of edges equals the number of constraints,
边的数量等于约束的数量
which is m, the height of the matrix,
就是m  也是矩阵的高度
and just transform. So, for example,
然后只要换算一下  举个例子
here we have three variables. So, we have three vertices,
这儿我们有三个变量 所以 我们有三个顶点
v_1, v_2, v_3. We have x_1 minus x_2.
v_1 v_2 v_3  我们有x_1 - x_2
So, we have an edge from v_2 to v_1 of weight three.
所以我们有一条从v_2到v_1的边  权值是3
We have x_2 minus x_3.
我们有x_2 - x_3
So, we have an edge from v_3 to v_2 of weight minus two.
所以 我们有一条从V3到V2的边  权值是-2
And, we have x_1 minus x_3.
然后我们于X1-X3
So, we have an edge from v_3 to v_1 of weight two.
所以 我们有一条边从v_3到v_1权值是2
I hope I got the directions right.
我希望我的方向是正确的
Yep. So, there it is, a graph
好的  这就是这个图
currently no obvious connection to shortest paths, right?
现在和最短路径看不出明显的联系 是么
But in fact,
但是 事实上
this constraint is closely related to shortest paths.
这个约束条件已经很接近最短路径了
So let me just rewrite it. You could say,
所以 让我来重写一遍  你可以说
well, an x_j is less than or equal to x_i plus w_ij.
x_j小于等于x_i + W_ij
Or, you could think of it
或者 你可以这么想
as d_j less than or equal to d_i plus w_ij.
d[j]小于等于d[i] + w_ij
This is a conceptual balloon.
这是一个泡泡里面是概念
Look awfully familiar?
是不是看上去好眼熟？
A lot like the triangle inequality, a lot like relaxation.
像极了三角不等式和松弛操作
So, there's a very close connection
所以 这里有一个很紧密的联系
between these two problems as we will now prove.
在这两个我们现在要证明的问题之间
So, we're going to have two theorems.
所以 我们会有两个定理
And, they're going to look similar to the correctness of
而且 它很像Bellman-ford在负权环中的正确性验证
Bellman-Ford in that they talk about negative weight cycles.
他们都讨论负权环的情况
Here we go. It turns out,
开始 它证明了
I mean, we have this constraint graph.
我们有这个约束图
It can have negative weights.
它可能有负权值
It can have positive weights.
也可能有正权值
It turns out what matters is
我们发现关键的是
if you have a negative weight cycle.
如果你有一个负权环
So, the first thing to prove is that
所以第一件要去证明的是
if you have a negative weight cycle
假如你有一个负权环
that something bad happens.
那就糟糕了
OK, what could happen bad?
什么糟糕的事情？
Well, we're just trying to
嗯哼  我们尝试着
satisfy this system of constraints.
满足这个约束式组
So, the bad thing is that there might not be any solution.
所以  最坏的事是这里可能无解
These constraints may be infeasible.
这些参数可能是不可行的
And that's the claim.
就是这样
The claim is that this is actually an if and only if.
这个理论实际上是“当且仅当”
But first we'll proved the if.
但是首先我们想证明“当”
If you have a negative weight cycle, you're doomed.
如果你只有一个负权环  你就gg吧
The difference constraints are unsatisfiable.
有些参数有可能不满足条件
That's a more intuitive way to say it.
只是比较直接地来解释它
In the LP world, they call it infeasible.
在线性规划里  它们叫做不可行的
But unsatisfiable makes a lot more sense.
但是说“不满足”更容易理解
There's no way to assign the x_i's in order to
没有办法找到一个x_i
satisfy all the constraints simultaneously.
来同时满足所有的限制条件
So, let's just take a look.
所以我们来看一下
Consider a negative weight cycle.
考虑一个负权环
It starts at some vertex, goes through some vertices,
它从某个顶点开始  经过了一些顶点
and at some point comes back.
在某些点又回来了
I don't care whether it repeats vertices,
我不在乎是否它重复了顶点
just as long as this cycle, from v_1 to v_1 is
只要这个循环  从v_1到v_1
a negative weight cycle, strictly negative weight.
是一个负权环  严格负的权值
OK, and what I'm going to do
好了  接下来我要做的是
is just write down all the constraints.
仅仅写下所有的系数
Each of these edges corresponds to a constraint,
这里的每一条边对应一个约束
which must be in the set of constraints
一定是这个约束集里某一个
because we had that graph.
因为我们有那个图
So, these are all edges. Let's look at what they give us.
这些是所有的边  让我们看一下它们给了我们什么
So, we have an edge from v_1 to v_2.
那么 我们有一条从v_1到v_2的边
That corresponds to x_2 minus x_1 is,
对应x_2 - x_1
at most, something, w_12.
最多是什么  是W_12
Then we have x_3 minus x_2.
然后我们有了x_3 - x_2
That's the weight w_23, and so on.
这是权值W_23   等等等等
And eventually we get up to something like x_k minus x_(k-1).
最终我们得到了一些像x_k - x_(k-1)
That's this edge: w_k minus 1, k ,
这是这条边 W_(k-1)k
and lastly we have this edge, which wraps around.
最后我们有了这条边  绕过来
So, it's x_1 minus x_k, w_k1 if I've got the signs right.
这是x_1 - x_k W_k1  如果符号对的话
Good, so here's a bunch of constraints.
好的  所以这里有一连串的约束
What do you suggest I do with them?
那要怎么处理？
Anything interesting about these constraints,
关于这些约束 有谁发现什么有趣的东西了没？
say, the left hand sides? Sorry?
我是说 在式子的左边？不好意思？
It sounded like the right word. What was it?
听上去像是正确答案  什么？
Telescopes, yes, good.
缩进法 对 很好
Everything cancels. If I added these up,
全部都抵消了  如果我把这些加上去
there's an x_2 and a minus x_2.
这里有一个x_2和一个 -x_2
There's a minus x_1 and an x_1.
这里有一个-x_1和一个x_1
There's a minus XK and an XK.
这里有个-x_k和一个x_k
Everything here cancels if I add up the left hand sides.
所有都抵消了  如果左手边加起来
So, what happens if I add up the right hand sides?
那么  如果右边加起来会发生什么？
Over here I get zero, my favorite answer.
到这里我得到零  我最喜欢的答案
And over here, we get all the weights
到这  我们得到了负权环里
of all the edges in the negative weight cycle,
所有边的权值
which is the weight of the cycle, which is negative.
就是循环的权值  是负的
So, zero is strictly less than zero: contradiction.
所以  零严格地小于零  矛盾
Contradiction, wait a minute,
矛盾  等一下
we didn't assume anything that was false.
我们并没有假设任何东西是错的
So, it's not really a contradiction
所以 这并不是一个真正的矛盾
in the mathematical sense.
在数学角度上
We didn't contradict the world.
我们并没有和世界矛盾
We just said that these constraints are contradictory.
我们只是说这些约束是矛盾的
In other words, if you pick any values of the x_i's,
换句话说 如果你取任何一个x_i的值
there is no way that these can all be true
没有办法说这些都可以成立
because that you would get a contradiction.
因为你会得到矛盾答案
So, it's impossible for these things to be satisfied
所以 对于这些约束来讲是不可能
by some real x_i's. So, these must be unsatisfiable.
由一些实数x_i满足   这些一定是不能满足的
Let's say there's no satisfying assignment,
我们说这里找不到一个皆大欢喜的解
a little more precise, x_1 up to x_m, no weights.
更准确地说  x_1直到x_m  都没有权值
can we satisfy those constraints
能够满足这些约束
Because they add up to zero on the left-hand side,
因为它们左手边加起来是零
and negative on the right-hand side.
右边加起来又是负的
OK, so that's an easy proof.
好的  这是一个简单的证明
The reverse direction will be only slightly harder.
反向证明会难一点点
OK, so, cool. We have this connection. So motivation is,
好  不错  我们有了个这个联系  所以我们要这样想
suppose you'd want to solve these difference constraints.
假设你想要解这些不等式组
And we'll see one such application.
我们将看到一个这样的应用
I Googled around for difference constraints.
我谷歌了下差分约束系统
There is a fair number of papers
有相当一部分这方面的研究
that care about difference constraints.
关于差分约束系统的
And, they all use shortest paths to solve them.
他们都用了最短路径来解决
So, if we can prove a connection between shortest paths,
所以 如果我们能证明最短路径——
which we know how to compute, and difference constraints,
这我们知道如何计算的——和差分约束系统的联系
then we'll have something cool.
我们将发现一些有趣的东西
And, next class will see
下一节课将会看到
even more applications of difference constraints.
甚至更多的关于差分约束系统的运用
It turns out they're really useful
你会发现它们真的很有用
for all pairs shortest paths.
对于全对最短路径问题来说
OK, but for now let's just prove
好了 不过现在让我们仅仅证明
this equivalence and finish it off.
这个等价关系  然后结束这节课
So, the reverse direction is if there's
所以这个反向证明是  如果
no negative weight cycle in this constraint graph,
在这个参数图里有负权环
then the system better be satisfiable. The claim is that
那么这个系统就应该是可以满足的  我们说
these negative weight cycles are the only barriers
这些负权环是唯一的障碍
for finding a solution to these difference constraints.
在求解这些不等式组的时候
I have this feeling somewhere here.
我在这里有一种感觉
I had to talk about the constraint graph. Good.
我得讲讲约束图  很好
Satisfied, good. So, here we're going to see a technique
满足的 很好 那么  我们将看到一个技巧
that is very useful when thinking about shortest paths.
当我们考虑最短路径问题的时候很有用
And, it's a bit hard to guess,
这有一点点难想到
especially if you haven't seen it before.
尤其是当你之前没有见过它的时候
This is useful in problem sets, and in quizzes,
在做练习和考试的时候很有用
and finals, and everything. So, keep this in mind.
所以  把这个记住
I mean, I'm using it to prove this rather simple theorem,
我的意思是  我证明它不仅是为了得到一个定理
but the idea of changing the graph,
更是要得到修改约束图的思想
so I'm going to call this constraint graph G.
我把这叫做约束图G
Changing the graph is a very powerful idea.
修改图是一个非常有用的想法
So, we're going to add a new vertex, s,
所以 我们就加一个新的顶点S
or source. Use the source,
或者源点  用这个源
look, and we're going to add a bunch of edges from s
看  我们还要加上一连串从s出发的边
because being a source,
因为作为一个初始点
it better be connected to some things.
它最好连上一些东西
So, we are going to add a zero weight edge,
所以我们将加一个零权值的边
or weight zero edge from s to everywhere,
或者从s到任何地方的零权值的边
so, to every other vertex in the constraint graph.
那么对于每个在参数图里的其他顶点
Those vertices are called v_i, v_1 up to v_n.
那些顶点被叫做v_i  v_1到v_n
So, I have my constraint graph.
这就是约束图
But I'll copy this one so I can change it.
我抄一遍  这样可以改写一下
It's always good to backup your work
备份总是明智的选择
before you make changes, right?
尤其是在你做些更改前  不是么
So now, I want to add a new vertex, s, over here,
所以现在 我想要加上一个新的顶点s 在这里
my new source. I just take my constraint graph,
我的新的源 我只是利用了我的参数图
whatever it looks like, add in weight zero edges
无论它是什么样的  加进零权重的边
to all the other vertices. Simple enough.
到所有其它的点上   灰常简单
Now, what did I do? What did you do?
现在  我做了什么？  你做了神马哇？
Well, I have a candidate source now
我现在有了一个候选源
which can reach all the vertices.
它可以到达所有的顶点
So, shortest path from s,
所以 从s的最短途径
hopefully, well, paths from s exist.
理想情况下 从s出发的路径是存在的
I can get from s to everywhere in weight at most zero.
我只要不超过零的权值 就可以从s到任何地方
OK, maybe less. Could it be less? Well, you know,
好了 可能小一些 它可以变小些么？  你看
like v_2, I can get to it by zero minus two.
像 v_2 我可以通过0-2来得到
So, that's less than zero.
所以 这比零小
So I've got to be a little careful.
所以这里我要小心一点
What if there's a negative weight cycle?
假设这里出现了负权环会怎样
Oh no? Then there wouldn't be any shortest paths.
雅蠛蝶啊  这样的话就不会有最短途径了
Fortunately, we assume that
幸运的是  我们假设
there's no negative weight cycle in the original graph.
在原图里没有负权环
And if you think about it,
如果你思考一下它
if there's no negative weight cycle in the original graph,
如果在原图里没有负权环
we add an edge from s to everywhere else.
我们加了一条从s到任何地方的边
We're not making any new negative weight cycles
我们没有做任何新的负权环
because you can start at s
因为你可以从s开始
and go somewhere at a cost of zero,
从s去某些地方的花费为0
which doesn't affect any weights.
这不影响任何权值
And then, you are forced to stay in the old graph.
然后 你们被强制留在旧图里
So, there can't be any new negative weight cycles.
所以 这不可能有任何新的负权环
So, the modified graph has no negative weight cycles.
所以 被修改的图没有负权环
That's good because it also has paths from s,
这不错 因为它也有从s出发的路径
and therefore it also has shortest paths from s.
因此它也有从s出发的最短路径
The modified graph has no negative weight
修改了的图没有负权值
because it didn't before. And, it has paths from s.
因为它之前并没有 然后 它有从s出发的路径
There's a path from s to every vertex.
这里有一条从s到每个顶点的路径
There may not have been before.
可能之前没有
Before, I couldn't get from v_2 to v_3, for example.
在之前 我不能从v_2到v_3  比如说
Well, that's still true.
好吧 现在仍然是这样
But from s I can get to everywhere.
但是从s出发我可以到任何地方
So, that means that this graph, this modified graph,
所以 这意味着这个图 这个修改后的图
has shortest paths. Shortest paths exist from s.
有最短路径 从s出发 最短路径存在
In other words, if I took all the shortest path weights,
换句话说 如果我取了所有的最短路径权值
like I ran Bellman-Ford from s, then,
像我从s起运行Bellman-ford算法 然后
I would get a bunch of finite numbers, d of v,
我能得到一连串有限的数字 d[v]
for every value, for every vertex.
对于每一个值 每一个顶点
That seems like a good idea. Let's do it.
这看上去是个好主意 让我们来试试
So, shortest paths exist.
所以 最短路径存在
Let's just assign x_i to be
让我们就标记x_i是
the shortest path weight from s to v_i.
从s到v_i的最短路径权值
Why not? That's a good choice for a number,
为什么不呢？  对于实际数字来说这样很好
This is finite because it's less than infinity,
这是有限的因为它比无穷大小
and it's greater than minus infinity,
而且它比无穷小大
so, some finite number.
所以 一些有限的数字
That's what we need to do
这就是需要用到的东西
in order to satisfy these constraints.
来满足这些约束条件
The claim is that this is a satisfying assignment.
这个观点是说这是个可以满足的工作
Why? Triangle inequality.
为什么？三角不等式
Somewhere here we wrote triangle inequality.
在这里某些地方我们写了三角不等式
This looks a lot like the triangle inequality.
这看上去很像三角不等式
In fact, I think that's the end of the proof.
事实上  我觉得这个快证完了
Let's see here.
我们看看
What we want to be true with this assignment is
我们想要的是确保成立的是
that x_j minus x_i is less than or equal to w_ij
x_j - x_i小于等于W_ij
whenever ij is an edge. Or, let's say v_i, v_j,
无论何时ij是一条边  或者我们说(v_i,v_j)
for every such constraint,
对于每一个这样的参数
so, for v_i, v_j in the edge set.
所以 对于在边集里的(v_i,v_j)
OK, so when is this true?
好  这个什么时候成立？
Well, let's just expand it out. So, x_i is this delta,
好吧 让我们先把它展开  所以x_i是这个δ
and x_j is some other delta. So, we have
而且x_j是另外的什么δ  所以我们有
delta of s,Vj minus delta of s, Vi. And, on the right-hand side,
δ(s,v_j)-δ(s,v_i)  然后在右手边
well, w_ij, that was the weight of the edge from i to j.
Wij 这是从i到j的边权
So, this is the weight of v_i to v_j.
所以 这是v_i到v_j的权值
OK, I will rewrite this slightly.
这里重新写一下
Delta s, vj is less than or equal to
δ(s,v_j) 小于等于
delta s, vi plus w of v_i, v_j.
δ(s,v_i)+W(v_i,v_j)
And that's the triangle inequality more or less.
这差不多就是个三角不等式
The shortest path from s to v_j is, at most,
从s到v_j的最短路径最多是
shortest path from s to v_i
是从s到v_j的最短路径
plus a particular path from v_i to v_j,
加上一条具体的从v_i到v_j的路径
namely the single edge v_i to v_j.
换句话说 从v_i到v_j的那条单边
This could only be longer than the shortest path.
这个只能比最短路径长
And so, that makes the right-hand side bigger,
所以 这令右手边数值变得更大
which makes this inequality more true,
这让这个不等式更加成立
meaning it was true before. And now it's still true.
就是说它以前成立  现在也还是成立
And, that proves it. This is true.
这就证明了 这个是成立的
And, these were all equivalent statements.
这些全都是平行的描述
This we know to be true by triangle inequality.
这些我们通过三角不等式证明这个是成立的
Therefore, these constraints are all satisfied.
因此  这些条件都被满足
Magic. I'm so excited here.
灰常神奇  我现在热情高涨啊
So, we've proved that
所以  我们已经证明了
having a negative weight cycle is exactly
负权环出现刚好是当
when these system of difference constraints are unsatisfiable.
这些不等式组不能被满足时
So, if we want to satisfy them,
所以  如果我们想要满足它们
if we want to find the right answer to x,
如果我们想要找到x的解
we run Bellman-Ford.
我们用Bellman-ford算法
Either it says, oh, no negative weight cycle.
要么它说  哦  不能给我负权环
Then you are hosed. Then, there is no solution.
然后你们被泼了一头冷水  然后 就没有然后了
But that's the best you could hope to know.
但这是你们能得到的最好的答案了
Otherwise, it says,
否则  它会说
oh, there was no negative weight cycle,
这里没有负权环
and here are your shortest path weights.
这是你们的最短路径权值
You just plug them in, and bang,
你们只要把它们代进去  然后 见证奇迹吧
you have your x_i's that satisfy the constraints.
你得到了满足这些约束条件的x_i
Awesome. Now, it wasn't just any graph.
很好 现在 它不只是图
I mean, we started with constraints, algebra,
我的意思是  我们从代数形式的约束开始
we converted it into a graph by this transform.
我们通过这种变换将它变成了图
Then we added a source vertex, s.
然后我们给图添加了一个源顶点s
So, I mean, we had to build a graph to solve our problem,
所以  我的意思是  我们要建立一个图来解决我们的问题
very powerful idea. Now we just plug in,
非常强大的想法  现在我们只用代进数值
Bellman-ford, and it gives us the answer.
运行Bellman-ford算法 结果就出来了
Cool. This is the idea of reduction.
酷  这是化简的想法
You can reduce the problem you want to
你可以把未知的问题
solve into some problem you know how to solve.
化简为已知的问题来解决掉
You know how to solve shortest paths
你知道如何解决最短路径
when there are no negative weight cycles, or find out that
如果是没有负权环的话  或者
there is a negative weight cycle by Bellman-Ford.
用Bellman-ford算法发现这里有一个的负权环
So, now we know how to solve difference constraints.
所以 现在我们知道如何来解不等式组了
It turns out you can do even more.
这说明  你甚至可以做更多
Bellman-Ford does a little bit more
Bellman-ford算法比
than just solve these constraints.
只是解决这些约束能做的更多
But first let me write down
但是首先让我写下来
what I've been jumping up and down about.
我之前强调的部分
The corollary is you can use Bellman-Ford.
这个推论你可以用Bellman-ford算法推导
I mean, you make this graph. Then you apply Bellman-Ford,
我的意思是 你做了这个图 然后你运用Bellman-ford算法
and it will solve your system of difference constraints.
然后它会解出你的差分约束不等式组
So, let me put in some numbers here.
所以 让我在这里给些数字
You have m difference constraints.
你有了m个不同的约束
And, you have n variables.
然后你有了n个变量
And, it will solve them in order m times n time.
然后它会在m*n时间内解出来
Actually, these numbers go up slightly
实际上 这些数字有些许增大
because we are adding n edges,
因为我们加上了n条边
and we're adding one vertex,
然后我们加上了一个顶点
but assuming all of these numbers are nontrivial,
但是假设所有的这些数字都是不可忽略的
m is at least n. It's order MN time.
m最小是n  那就是O(mn)时间
OK, trying to avoid cases
好了 尝试着避免这类情况
where some of them are close to zero.
它们中的一些接近零
Good. So, some other facts,
好  所以一些其他的情况
that's what I just said.
就如我刚刚所说的
And we'll leave these as exercises
我们将要留下这些作为练习
because they're not too essential.
因为它们没有那么重要
The main thing we need is this.
我们需要的主要的是这个
But, some other cool facts is that
但是 一些其他神奇的东西是
Bellman-Ford actually optimizes some objective functions.
Bellman-ford算法事实上优化了一些目标函数
So, we are saying it's just a feasibility problem.
所以 我们在说它只是一个可行性问题
We just want to know
我们只是想知道
whether these constraints are satisfiable.
这些约束是否可以被满足
In fact, you can add a particular objective function.
事实上 你可以加上一个具体的目标函数
So, you can't give it an arbitrary objective function,
所以 你不能给他一个随机的目标函数
but here's one of interest. X_1 plus x_2 plus x_n,
但是这里有一个有趣的  x_1+x_2+……+x_n
OK, but not just that. We have some constraints.
好吧 但不只是那样 我们有一些约束
OK, this is a linear program. I want to maximize the sum of
这是线性规划  我想要最大化
the x_i's subject to all the x_i's being nonpositive
所有x_i的和   并满足所有x_i都是非正数的条件下
and the difference constraints. So, this we had before.
以及这个差分约束不等式组  这个前面有了
This is fine. We noticed at some point
这很好  我们注意到在某个点s
you could get from s to everywhere with cost, at most,
你可以只用不超过0的代价到达任何地方
zero. So, we know that in this assignment
那么 我们知道在这道题里
all of the x_i's are negative.
所有的x_i是负的
That's not necessary,
这没有必要
but it's true when you run Bellman-Ford.
但是当你运行Bellman-ford算法 你会发现的确是这样
So if you solve your system using Bellman-Ford,
所以如果你用Bellman-ford解一个问题
which is no less general than anything else,
这不比其他任何事特殊
you happen to get nonpositive x_i's.
你也是会得到非正的x_i
And so, subject to that constraint,
所以  由于约束的限制
it actually makes them is
它实际上让它们在
close to zero as possible in the L1 norm.
L1范数内尽可能地趋近0
In the sum of these values,
对于这些值的总和
it tries to make the sum as close to zero,
它使这个和尽可能地靠近了零
it tries to make the values
它尝试着让这个值的绝对值里尽可能的小
OK, it does more than that.
好了 它还可以做得更多
It cooks, it cleans, it finds shortest paths.
它做饭 它打扫 它找到了最短路径
It also minimizes the spread, the maximum over all i of x_i
它同时使广度最小化   也就是x_i中的最大值
minus the minimum over all of x_i.
减去x_i中的最小值
So, I mean, if you have your real line,
所以 我的意思是 如果画一条实数轴
and here are the x_i's wherever they are.
然后这里是x_i们  随便它们在哪里
It minimizes this distance.
它最小化了这段距离
And zero is somewhere over here.
而零在这里的某个地方
So, it tries to make the x_i's as compact as possible.
所以 它尝试让x_i尽可能的紧密
This is actually the L infinity norm,
这实际上是L无限范数
if you know stuff about norms
如果你知道些关于范数的东西
from your linear algebra class.
在你的线性代数课上
OK, this is the L1 norm.
好吧 这是L1范数
I think it minimizes every LP norm.
我认为它最小化了每一个线性规划范数
Good, so let's use this for something.
很好 所以 让我们用它来干点什么吧
Yeah, let's solve a real problem,
让我们来解个题
and then we'll be done for today.
然后我们今天的课就结束了
Next class we'll see the really cool stuff,
下一节课我们会看到真正神奇的东西
the really cool application of all of this.
关于这些东西的神奇应用
For now, and we'll see a cool
现在 我们将看一个很帅气
but relatively simple application,
又很简明的应用
which is VLSI layout.
也就是VLSI
We talked a little bit about VLSI way back
我们讨论过一点 VLSI回路的问题
and divide and conquer.
分治法问题
You have a bunch of chips, or you want to arrange them,
你们有一连串的集成电路片 你想要调整它们
and minimize some objectives. So, here's a particular,
让某些值最小化 所以  这里有一个
tons of problems that come out of VLSI layout.
从VLSI设计中引申出来的具体问题
Here's one of them.
这里是其中一个
You have a bunch of features of an integrated circuit.
你有一堆的集成电路的零件
You want to somehow arrange them on your circuit
你想要以某种方法在你的回路里调整它们
without putting any two of them too close to each other.
不让其中任意两个过于靠近
You have some minimum separation
你至少要有一点距离
like at least they should not get top of each other.
像至少它们不能叠在一起
Probably, you also need some separation
也许你要多点空间
to put wires in between, and so on,
来在中间布线等等
so, without putting any two features too close together.
所以  不把任意两个放置过近
OK, so just to give you an idea, so I have some objects
好了 所以只是给你们一个想法  所以我有一些目标
and I'm going to be
对于这个过程
a little bit vague about how this works.
也不用说得太细
You have some features.
你有一些零件
This is stuff, some chips, whatever.
这是材料  集成电路片  等等一些玩意
We don't really care what their shapes look like.
不管它们是什么形状
I just want to be able to move them around
我只是想能够移动它们
so that the gap at any point,
来让任意点间的间距
so let me just think about this gap.
就比如说这个间距
This gap should be at least some delta.
这个间距应该最少是一些δ
Or, I don't want to use delta.
或者我不想用δ
Let's say epsilon, good, small number.
让我们用ε  很好 即小数字
So, I just need some separation between all of my parts.
所以  我仅需要分离一下各部分
And for this problem, I'm going to be pretty simple,
对于这个问题十分简单
just say that the parts
就是说那些部分
are only allowed to slide horizontally.
是只被允许水平地滑动
So, it's a one-dimensional problem.
所以 这是一个一维问题
These objects are in 2-d,
这些物体是在二维平面里的
or whatever, but I can only slide them an x coordinate.
或者无论如何  但是我只能够在x坐标里移动它们
So, to model that,
所以  如果要建模
I'm going to look at the left edge of every part and say,
我将要看每一部分的左边缘  然后说
well, these two left edges should be
这两个左边缘之间
at least some separation.
至少是有一点距离
So, I think of it as whatever
所以我这样想
the distance is plus some epsilon. But, you know,
无论如何这个距离是加上了一些ε  但是你知道
if you have some funky 2-d shapes you have to compute,
如果你要计算一些诡异的二维图形
well, this is a little bit too close
这有一点太近了
because these come into alignment.
因为这些属于一条直线
But, there's some constraint, well, for any two pieces,
但是 这里有一些系数 对于任何的两片
I could figure out how close they can get.
我能够计算出它们能靠多近
They should get no closer. So, I'm going to call this x_1.
它们应该不能再近了  那么我把这个标为x_1
I'll call this x_2. So, we have some constraint
这个标为x_2  那么  我们有了一些约束
like x_2 minus x_1 is at least d plus epsilon,
像x_2 - x_1最少是d+ε
or whatever you compute that weight to be.
或者无论你算出的权重是什么
OK, so for every pair of pieces, I can do this,
所以对于每一对零件 我可以做相同的事
compute some constraint on how far apart they have to be.
计算一些关于它们距离多远的约束
And, now I'd like to assign these x coordinates.
现在我想要给这些x标上坐标
Right now, I'm assuming they're just variables.
现在 我假设它们只是变量
I want to slide these pieces around horizontally in order to
我想要水平地滑动这些零件为了
compactify them as much as possible
尽可能的使他们紧密
so they fit in the smallest chip
以便把它们装进尽可能小的电路片里
that I can make because it costs money,
因为大电路板要花费更多的钱
and time, and everything, and power, everything.
和时间 和任何东西 能量神马的
You always want your chip small.
你总是想要你的集成电路很小
So, Bellman-Ford does that.
那么Bellman-ford算法实现了这个
All right, so Bellman-Ford solves these constraints
所以Bellman-ford解出了这些约束
because it's just a bunch of difference constraints.
因为它只是一堆不等式组
And we know that they are solvable
我们知道它们是可以解决的
because you could spread all the pieces out arbitrarily far.
因为你可以把这些零件用任意距离分开
And, it minimizes the spread,
而且 它最小化了这些宽度
minimizes the size of the chip I need,
最小化了我所需集成电路的大小
a max of x_i minus the min of x_i.
最大的x_i值减去最小的x_i值
So, this is it maximizes compactness,
那么  这就是集成的最大化
or minimizes size of the chip.
或者体积的最小化集成电路
OK, this is a one-dimensional problem,
好了 这是一维问题
so it may seem a little artificial,
所以它可能看上去是刻意为之
but the two dimensional problem is really hard to solve.
但是二维问题实在很难去解决
And this is, in fact,
就是这个了  事实上
the best you can do with a nice polynomial time algorithm.
这是在不错的多项式时间内解决的最好做法了
There are other applications if you're scheduling events in,
这里有一些其他运用  比如你在把一些事件剪辑进
like, a multimedia environment,
呃  像是多媒体中
and you want to guarantee that this audio plays
而且你想要保证这音频
at least two seconds after this video,
至少在视频的两秒后播放
but then there are things that are playing at the same time,
然后也有要同时播放的东西
and they have to be within some gap of each other,
而且它们必须彼此之间有一定的间隔
so, lots of papers about using Bellman-Ford,
所以 有许多关于使用Bellman-ford的研究
solve difference constraints
来解决不同的约束
to enable multimedia environments.
来建立多媒体文件
OK, so there you go.
好了  就是这样
And next class we'll see
下一节课我们会看到
more applications of Bellman-Ford to
关于Bellman-ford算法更多的运用
all pairs shortest paths. Questions?
来解决全对的最短路径  有问题么
Great.
非常好